Guide to the David Gordon George Papers, 1919-1976 and undated, bulk 1935-1965 RL.00441
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
David Gordon George papers
1919-1976 and undated, bulk 1935-1965
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
George, David Gordon
RL.00441
6.9 Linear Feet 3400 items
Resident of Richmond, Va., socialist and grassroots political activist in his early life; founder of the Southern Electoral Reform League; later sided with conservatives such as Barry Goldwater and George Wallace. The David Gordon George Papers span the years 1919 to 1976, with the bulk of the collection dated between 1935 and 1965, and are organized into the Correspondence, Personal Files, Printed Materials and Writings, Photographic Materials, and Subject Files Series. The collection consists primarily of correspondence and files related to George's involvement in a variety of political and social movements, documenting his early involvement in grassroots socialist and leftist democratic organizing and electoral reform work, decades of involvement with national and regional labor organizations, and his late-life support of anti-communist and socially conservative politics, including segregationist platforms. His complex views on the political and social status of African Americans in the South, particularly in Virginia, are documented in his writings and correspondence. Among the organizations well-represented in the collection are the Southern Electoral Reform League, the Virginia Electoral Reform League, and the United States Information Service. The papers include correspondence with a wide spectrum of national political leaders, from Socialists (Norman Thomas and Victor Berger) to Democrats (Hubert Humphrey and Estes Kefauer) to Conservatives (George Wallace), as well as staff of diverse labor organizations and a number of Virginia politicians across a broad ideological spectrum. Acquired as part of the George Washington Flowers Collection of Southern Americana.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The David Gordon George Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in May 2003, with an addition purchased in 2014.
Biographical Note
Chronology
1910 Apr. 5 David Gordon George born to David Graves George and Maria Murphy George in Danville, Virginia
1926-1928 Worked for Socialist Party in Virginia and New York
1927 Graduated from Chester High School, Chester, Virginia
1929-1930 Attended Rand School of Social Science, New York, New York
1934 Formally broke from Socialist Party
1936-1940 Worker on family farm in Beaverdam, Virginia, and freelance writer for newspapers in Richmond, Virginia
1939 Founded Southern Electoral Reform League
1939 Ran for Virginia House of Delegates seat as an independent
1941 Ran for primary for Virginia House of Delegates seat as a Democrat
1942-1945 Virginia Labor Relations Representative for War Production Board
1944-1945 Chairman, Richmond British Service Entertainment Committee
1945 Managed Moss A. Plunkett's gubernatorial campaign in Virginia
1946-1948 Lectured in Great Britain, initially with U.S. Information Agency
1950 Upper South Political Action Director for Textile Workers Union of America
1951-1953 Worked for Wage Stabilization Board in Richmond, Virginia
1954-1958 Involved in mineral exploration venture in Chihuahua, Mexico
1956 June 16 Married Ana Maria Delgado in Las Cruces, New Mexico
1957 Twin daughters Ana Elizabeth and Maria Linda George born
1959-1961 Worked as a labor representative as part of a United Textile Workers Union strike in Henderson, NC
1962 Application for employment with U.S. Foreign Service rejected to due concerns of Communist sympathies
1965-1969 Worked for United Planning Organization in Washington, DC
1970-1972 Worked as a teacher and administrator at Bermuda Academy, Hopewell, Virginia
1976 Died in Richmond, Virginia
Collection Overview
The David Gordon George Papers span the years 1919 to 1976, with the bulk of the collection dated between 1935 and 1965, and are organized into the Correspondence, Personal Files, Printed Materials and Writings, Photographic Materials, and Subject Files Series. The collection consists primarily of correspondence and files related to George's involvement in a variety of political and social movements, documenting his early involvement in grassroots socialist and leftist democratic organizing and electoral reform work, decades of involvement with national and regional labor organizations, and his late-life support of anti-communist and socially conservative politics. His complex views on the political and social status of African Americans in the South, particularly in Virginia, are documented in his writings and correspondence. Among the organizations well-represented in the collection are the Southern Electoral Reform League, founded by George primarily to campaign against poll taxes, and the United States Information Service. The papers include files of correspondence with a wide spectrum of prominent national political leaders, from Socialists (Norman Thomas and Victor Berger) to Democrats (Hubert Humphrey and Estes Kefauer) to Conservatives (George Wallace), as well as staff of diverse labor organizations and a number of Virginia politicians across a broad ideological spectrum. There are also several files of correspondence relating to George's business ventures in Mexico, particularly his interests and operations in mining in the Chihuahua region.
George's writings, including many editorials and letters to the editor, and correspondence reveal his complex and shifting allegiances to various reform organizations during particularly eventful decades for the labor movement in the U.S. His work for labor-related causes in different guises put him in at least tacit opposition to positions he had advocated earlier. He also offers often contradictory views on race, supporting local black politicians at one point but joining the segregationist Citizens Council later in his life. In addition, George's experiences during the McCarthy Era demonstrate the lasting professional consequences of the alleged Communist ties in his past.
Acquired as part of the George Washington Flowers Collection of Southern Americana.
Southern States -- Race relations; Scrapbooks; Southern States -- Politics and government -- 1950-; Photographs; Ephemera; Southern States -- Politics and government -- 1865-1950; Tungsten mines and mining -- Mexico.; Southern States -- Economic conditions; United States -- Politics and government -- 1933-1945; United States -- Politics and government -- 1919-1933; Suffrage -- Southern States; Whites -- Southern States -- Politics and government -- 20th century; Elections -- Virginia; Virginia -- Politics and government -- 1865-1950; Elections -- United States; Election law -- United States; Conservatism -- Southern States -- History; Labor -- United States; Virginia -- Politics and government -- 1951-; Labor and laboring classes -- Southern States; Socialist parties -- United States; Labor unions -- Southern States; African Americans -- Virginia; Political activists -- Southern States; Labor unions -- United States -- 1930-1970; Conservatism -- United States -- History; Conservatism -- Southern States; Anti-communist movements -- United States; Conservatism -- United States; Socialists -- United States -- Correspondence; Socialism -- United States; Poll tax -- Southern States; Clippings (information artifacts); Political activists -- United States; Rhetoric -- Poltical aspects -- Southern States -- History -- 20th century; United States -- Politics and government -- 1945-1989; Poll tax -- Virginia; George, David Gordon; George, David Gordon, 1910-1976; Kefauver, Estes, 1903-1963; Humphrey, Hubert H. (Hubert Horatio), 1911-1978; Thomas, Norman, 1884-1968; Southern Electoral Reform League; Wallace, George C. (George Corley), 1919-1998; United States Information Agency; Berger, Victor L., 1860-1929; George Washington Flowers Collection of Southern Americana
- Correspondence Series, 1922-1975 and undated, 4 boxes
  Scope and Contents note
  Incoming correspondence primarily consists of cards and personal letters from friends and family. While friends and colleagues in various political organizations discuss business matters in letters in this series, topics discussed are generally of a personal nature. A substantial number of letters are from men in the British armed forces, contacts apparently made while George was involved with the British Service Entertainment Committee in Richmond. Many of these letters are filed in the "unknown/unnamed" correspondence file because only first names or nicknames were included in the letter.
  The political correspondence contains letters to and from officials and their staff in the organizations with which George was involved through his life, both as a socialist in the 1930s and as a conservative in the 1960s and 1970s. Prominent national leaders with whom George corresponded include the socialist U.S. Congressmen Victor Berger and George M. Rhodes as well as Barry Goldwater, Estes Kefauer, and others. Substantial correspondence with Hubert Humphrey is also included. Additional notable national political figures include Norman Thomas, Upton Sinclair, Gardner Jackson, Arthur McDowell, Nelson Rockefeller, and George Wallace. In addition, George corresponded with a number of prominent Virginia politicians. Many of the letters in this section are generic testimonials to George's good character or are updates about possible employment opportunities, though some also discuss specific political matters.
  Another significant portion of correspondence, received as part of a later accession, documents George's interests and operations in Mexico mining, particularly tungsten mining in the Chihuahua region. This correspondence largely dates from 1954. Substantial additional correspondence can be found in the Subject Files Series and in the Personal Files Series.
  Correspondence has been loosely arranged by correspondent's last name, with scattered "general" folders throughout the series. Many of the larger name files relate to George's Mexican mining exploits. General folders tend to include earlier letters from a wider variety of correspondents. There is also a folder of correspondence from the George family, with many letters to George from his mother and siblings.
  - Incoming cards, 1936-1974 and undated (Box 1)
  - Abbitt, Watkins M., 1948-1971 (Box 2)
  - Arredondo, Raul, 1954 (Box 2)
  - Re: Auto-Bond, 1955 (Box 2)
  - General, A-B, 1922-1973 (Box 2)
  - Bencomo, Emilio, and Associates, 1955 (Box 2)
  - Berger, Victor, 1928 July-Dec. (Box 2)
  - Bolling, Richard (Box 2)
  - Buckman, H.H., 1954 (Box 2)
  - Christopher, George H., 1955-1958 (Box 2)
  - General, C-D, 1925-1973 (Box 2)
  - Dabney, Virginius, 1937-1964 (Box 2)
  - Delson, Harry; Delson, Levin, and Gordon, 1954 (Box 2)
  - Denver Equipment Co., 1954 (Box 2)
  - Edelman, John, 1954 (Box 2)
  - Evans, David L., 1954-1956 (Box 2)
  - General, E-F, 1938-1975 (Box 2)
  - Fliesler, Joseph, 1954 (Box 2)
  - Fowler and Symington, 1954 (Box 2)
  - Garcia Moreno, Alfredo, 1955 (Box 2)
  - Garcia-Gutierrez, 1954 (Box 2)
  - Gardea T., D., 1955-1956 (Box 2)
  - Gary, Vaughan, 1947-1948 (Box 13)
  - George family, 1930s-1940s (Box 13)
  - George, Herbert, 1956 (Box 13)
  - Goldwater, Barry, 1964 (Box 13)
  - Grey, Charles E., 1954 (Box 13)
  - General, G-J, 1925-1963 (Box 13)
  - Hammerton, Vic, 1945-1951 (Box 13)
  - Hippelheuser, R. H., 1954 and undated (Box 13)
  - Hofheimer, H. C., II, 1954-1956, 3 folders (Box 13)
  - Howell, Charles, 1954 (Box 13)
  - Humphrey, Hubert, 1949-1962 (Box 13)
  - Jackson, Gardner, 1942-1963 (Box 13)
  - Kampelman, Max, 1955-1959 (Box 13)
  - Kashouty, Henry, 1954 (Box 13)
  - Kefauver, Estes, 1954-1961 (Box 13)
  - Koslow, Nathan, 1954 (Box 13)
  - General, K-M, 1945-1973 (Box 13)
  - Marks, C. Hardaway, 1954 (Box 13)
  - McDowell, Arthur G. (Council Against Communist Aggression), 1962-1964 (Box 13)
  - McWilliams, Charles, 1962-1964 (Box 14)
  - Mendes, Toby E., 1953-1954 (Box 14)
  - Michael, Lawrence, 1964 (Box 14)
  - Murray, Isabel, 1954-1956 (Box 14)
  - General, N-R, 1922-1954 and undated (Box 14)
  - Plunkett, Moss, 1942-1956 (Box 14)
  - Republican National Committee, 1964-1965 (Box 14)
  - Rhodes, George M., 1954-1961 (Box 14)
  - Rockefeller, Nelson, 1962 (Box 14)
  - General, S-T, 1938-1968 (Box 14)
  - Scott, William L., 1966-1967 (Box 14)
  - Servin, Manuel Torres, 1954 (Box 14)
  - Sinclair, Upton, 1937-1939 (Box 14)
  - Staggers, Harley O., 1954-1962
  - Thomas, Norman, 1928-1939 (Box 14)
  - Tuck, William M., 1963 (Box 14)
  - General, U, 1954 (Box 14)
  - Vargas, Bonifacio, 1956 (Box 14)
  - Visconti, Arcangel, 1954 (Box 14)
  - Wah Chang Corp., 1954 (Box 1954)
  - Wallace, George C., 1963-1969 (Box 14)
  - Weymouth, Daniel, 1954 (Box 14)
  - General, W-Z, 1945-1946 (Box 14)
  - Unknown/unnamed correspondents (Box 14)
- Subject Files Series, 1925-1973 and undated, 6 boxes
  Contains files, clippings, and correspondence relevant to George's involvement with a number of interrelated causes and concerns, chiefly with Virginia politics. Included are materials concerning his races for seats in the Virginia House of Delegates in 1939 and 1941. George's work for political reform, particularly as founder of the Southern Electoral Reform League, is addressed primarily in the Electoral Reform subseries, though information on this topic can also be found in the subseries African American Virginians, and Elections. His interest in the labor movement in the United States and abroad is covered in the Labor subseries, with additional materials located in the Socialist Activites and War Production Board subseries. Researchers interested in the socialist movement in the South should consult materials in the Electoral Reform subseries as well as the Socialist Activites subseries. Papers in the African American Virginians subseries reveal George's complex views on race relations when coupled with materials in the Citizens Council subseries. Additional materials on this subject can be found in correspondence housed in the Personal Files series. George's work and interest in foreign relations can be found in the Foreign Affairs and British Service Entertainment Committee subseries. Substantial files and correspondence related to George's several-year foray into mineral prospecting can be found in the Mexico Mining Venture subseries. Organized alphabetically.
  - African American Virginians
    - Black Richmond and Virginia leaders, 1933-1949 (Box 3)
    - Civil Rights Committee of Richmond, 1949-1951 (Box 3)
    - Negro voting, 1943-1948 (Box 3)
    - Virginia politics--old info, 1940-1947 (Box 3)
    - Voters' League, 1950-1961 (Box 3)
  - British Service Entertainment Committee
    - Correspondence, 1944 Sept.-1945 Feb. (Box 3)
    - Hospitality lists-etc., 1944-1970 (Box 3)
    - Loose materials, 1944 Oct. 11-17 (Box 3)
    - Minutes and general, 1944 May-Nov. (Box 3)
    - Photographs, [1944] Aug. 20-Sept. 10, undated, 3 folders (Box 3)
    - Programs, [1944] Sept. 9-1945 Jan. 13, 7 folders (Box 3)
    - Reams, Ellen Walsh, songwriter, 1943-1944 (Box 3)
    - Suggestions to hosts and hostesses, [1944] Oct. 11 (Box 3)
    - Treasury correspondence, 1944 Apr.-1945 Apr. (Box 3)
  - Citizens' Council
    - Correspondence and files, 1964 Sept. 15-1965 Jan. 3 (Box 3)
  - Elections
    - Campaign materials, 1941-1952, 4 folders (Box 3)
    - Election statistics, 1928-1949, 6 folders (Box 3)
    - Fourth District campaigns, 1945-1948 (Box 3)
    - 1939 George campaign, 1939-1941 (Box 3)
    - 1941 George campaign, 1941 Apr.-July (Box 4)
    - Hart, James P., Jr., 1947 (Box 4)
    - Itineraries, 1945 July (Box 4)
    - Miller, Francis P., 1948 July-Dec. (Box 4)
    - Plunkett, Moss A. campaign, 1945, 3 folders (Box 4)
    - Plunkett, Moss A. campaign correspondence, 1945 July 12-29 (Box 4)
    - Plunkett, W.C., 1945 July (Box 4)
    - Political analyses, 1946-1953 (Box 4)
    - Political correspondence, 1952-1953 (Box 4)
    - Press releases, 1945 June-July (Box 4)
    - Roosevelt Club, 1935 Aug.-Sept. (Box 4)
    - Speeches, 1945 July-Aug. (Box 4)
    - Welsted, I.C., 1945 July (Box 4)
    - White, Randolph, 1945 July (Box 4)
    - Williams, Martha, 1945 (Box 4)
  - Electoral Reform
    - Millis, Mary Raoul, 1935-1958 (Box 4)
    - Poll Tax, 1937-1942 (Box 4)
    - Southern Electoral Reform League (SERL), 1940-1949, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - SERL-Virginia Electoral Reform League (VERL)-Virginia Commonwealth League (VCL), etc., 1940-1949 (Box 5)
    - Virginia Electoral Reform League, 1943-1944 (Box 5)
    - VERL, VCL, etc., 1944-1950, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Foreign Affairs
    - Cunard White Star, 1946-1948 (Box 5)
    - English-Speaking Union, 1947-1948 (Box 5)
    - Foreign office, etc., 1946 Aug.-Nov. (Box 5)
    - Parcels--overseas, undated (Box 5)
    - South Africa, 1963-1965 (Box 5)
    - South Africa lists-materials, 1963-1965 (Box 5)
    - South Africa Summary and Scope, 1937-1964 (Box 5)
    - United States Information Service (USIS)--Embassy, 1946-1947 (Box 5)
    - USIS Papers and Letters, 1962-1970 (Box 5)
  - Labor
    - Congress of Industrial Organizations Political Action Committee (CIO-PAC), 1962-1970 (Box 5)
    - Detroit strikes, 1937 (Box 5)
    - Edelman, John W., 1949-1963 (Box 5)
    - Gabor, Robert, 1961-1962 (Box 5)
    - Gilbert, David M., 1949 May-June (Box 5)
    - Henderson--earmarked fund, 1960-1961 (Box 5)
    - Henderson--Freedom Fighters Relief Committee (FFC) Materials, 1961-1962 (Box 5)
    - Henderson--FFC Reports, 1959-1962 (Box 6)
    - International Union of Electrical, Radio, and Machine Workers, AFL-CIO, (IUE), 1963 (Box 6)
    - Labor articles and papers, 1942-1961 (Box 6)
    - Levy, Capt. Nathan, 1958 May-Aug. (Box 6)
    - Lewis, Marx, 1962-1964 (Box 6)
    - McCallister, Frank, 1941-1963, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - McDowell, Arthur G., 1949 July 22-28 (Box 6)
    - McGill, James H., 1942-1948 (Box 6)
    - Textile Workers Union of America (TWUA), 1950-1961 (Box 6)
    - Webber, Charles C., 1949 Mar.-May (Box 6)
  - Mexico Mining Venture
    - Agreements and contracts, 1954-1955 (Box 6)
    - Assays etc., 1955 July-Oct. (Box 6)
    - Barraza, Samuel, 1957-1961 (Box 6)
    - Bernfeld, Cyril and Hollander, 1957-1958 (Box 6)
    - Correspondence and papers, 1956-1962, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Contracts etc.--San Jose, 1955 (Box 6)
    - El Dorado, 1957 Aug.-Sept. (Box 6)
    - Evans, David L., 1957-1962, 3 folders (Box 6)
    - Expense accounts and estimates, 1955-1956 (Box 6)
    - Expense accounts, 1954 (Box 1)
    - Gardea T., 1957-1958 (Box 7)
    - Guerra Hardware Co., 1954-1956 (Box 7)
    - Hofheimer, H.C., II, 1957-1962 (Box 7)
    - Investment agreements, 1954-1955 (Box 7)
    - Kashouty, Henry D., 1955-1956 (Box 7)
    - Loeb, Carl M., Jr., 1955-1957 (Box 7)
    - Maps and sketches, 1955, undated (Box 7)
    - Memoranda, 1954-1957, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Mining and tax laws, 1956 Jan. 4 (Box 7)
    - Miscellaneous--Breit-Fergusun-Amicus Most-Etc., 1957 Mar.-Oct. (Box 7)
    - Outlying properties, 1955-1956 (Box 7)
    - Prieto, Raphael, 1958-1959 (Box 7)
    - Reports and statements re: tungsten mining venture, 1954 (Box 14)
    - Tinoco, Ing. Luis, 1956-1957 (Box 7)
    - Trustees report etc., 1954 July-Aug. (Box 7)
    - Von Schoech, Ann Shepard, etc., 1966-1973 (Box 7)
    - Visa endorsements etc., 1937-1957 (Box 7)
  - Socialist Activities
    - Americans for Democratic Action, 1945-1947 (Box 7)
    - Clippings, 1933-1945, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Correspondence and party materials, 1925-1934, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Germany etc., 1927-1939 (Box 7)
    - New Leader, 1946-1949 (Box 7)
    - Pelman Institute, 1926 Dec. (Box 8)
    - Photographs, 1935 (Box 8)
    - Socialist organization papers, 1933-1965 (Box 8)
  - War Production Board
    - Cary, Hunson, 1942 Aug.-Oct. (Box 8)
    - Endorsements, misc. letters, etc., 1937-1952 (Box 8)
    - Memo--post-war trade, 1943 Apr. 28 (Box 8)
    - War Production Board, 1934-1954 (Box 8)
- Personal Papers Series, 1925-1973 and undated, 1 box
  Comprises papers and correspondence from George's early school years through his final years of life. Debate materials and schoolwork as well as materials related to George's high school reunions are housed in this series. The bulk of the materials relate to George's employment history, particularly his struggles to secure a job with the U.S. government in his later life after being labeled a Communist by the FBI. Copies of George's applications to the U.S. Information Agency and subsequent complaints of bias during required background checks are housed in this series. Additional correspondence on this subject can be found in the political correspondence section. Legal complaints relating to a reference to him as a "socialist" in the newspaper and for wrongful termination are included as well. Finally, correspondence in this series includes a number of letters of complaints about service received at various institutions late in his life. Organized alphabetically by folder title.
  - Background--political, 1962 Sept.-Oct. (Box 8)
  - Book of phone numbers, business cards, etc. (Box 15)
  - Clippings, 1942-1974 (Box 8)
  - Clippings, 1960s, 3 folders (Box 15)
  - Correspondence, 1968-1975 (Box 8)
  - Draft records, 1940-1946 (Box 8)
  - Early school years, 1925-1948 (Box 8)
  - Employment file resource, 1962, undated (Box 8)
  - Maps and blueprints (Box 1)
  - Mutual funds (Box 1)
  - Personal, 1943-1953 (Box 8)
  - Personal, legal, and financial papers, 1925-1973 (Box 8)
  - Personal references, 1934-1963 (Box 8)
  - School reunions, 1963-1967 (Box 8)
  - Special personal, 1943-1946 (Box 8)
  - Visas to U.S., 1957-1963 (Box 8)
- Photographic Materials, 1926-1953 and undated, 2 Folders
  Consists of photographs of George and members of his family, as well as some photographs of George with some of his political contacts. Notable examples include photos of Eleanor Roosevelt and Hubert Humphrey, as well as an autographed photo of country and labor singer "Texas" Bill Strength. A number of vacation slides are housed in this collection as well. Organized as received.
  - Photographs (Box 8)
- Printed Materials and Writings Series, 1937-1974 and undated, 1 box
  Contains articles and drafts of articles written by George for newspapers and magazines as well as some scripts written for radio. Limited correspondence relating to George's attempts to get his work published in magazines is also included in this series. The majority of the articles in this series were written for Virginia newspapers, mainly the Richmond Times-Dispatch. Larger copies of and clippings from newspapers have been moved to Oversize Materials.
  - Articles and letters to editors, 1962-1972, undated, 2 folders (Box 9)
  - Barbaric Thugs--and British Workers, 1947 (Box 9)
  - The Ebb and Flow of American Radicalism, undated (Box 9)
  - Harper's article, 1947-1952 (Box 9)
  - Lecture correspondence, 1946-1947 (Box 9)
  - Letters to editors and response, 1947-1974 (Box 9)
  - Magazine articles, 1949-1961 and undated (Box 9)
  - Notes etc., 1964-1970 and undated (Box 9)
  - Notes for speeches, undated (Box 9)
  - Radio scripts and correspondence, 1948-1950 (Box 9)
  - Richmond newspaper articles, 1937; 2 folders (Box 9)